---
title: "1.6.6. Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims"
read_title: "Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims"
slug: "lesson-1.6.6"
estimated_hours: 1
learning_outcomes:
  - to establish understanding on the importance of facilitating maritime traffic
  - to establish understanding on a purpose of the LLMC convention;
  - to analyse the concept of limitation of shipowner’s liability under the LLMC;
  - to comment the concept of maritime claim and its importance in limitation of shipowner’s liability;
  - to distinguish between the types of maritime claims which are covered by the LLMC;
  - to present the principles of calculation of limit of shipowner’s liability under the LLMC;
  - to analyse importance of Protocol, 1996 to LLMC.

links:
  - "Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims, 1976, available at the United Nations Treaty Collection: [https://treaties.un.org/pages/showDetails.aspx?objid=08000002800f9404](https://treaties.un.org/pages/showDetails.aspx?objid=08000002800f9404)"
  - "Protocol of 1996 to amend the Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims, 1976, London, 2 May 1996, available at: [https://cil.nus.edu.sg/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1996-LLMC-Prot.pdf](https://cil.nus.edu.sg/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/1996-LLMC-Prot.pdf)"
  - "IMO Resolution A.898(21), adopted on 25 November 1999, Guidelines on shipowners’ responsibilities in respect of maritime claims, available at: [https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/KnowledgeCentre/IndexofIMOResolutions/AssemblyDocuments/A.898(21).pdf](<https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/KnowledgeCentre/IndexofIMOResolutions/AssemblyDocuments/A.898(21).pdf>)"
  - "Directive 2009/20/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 April 2009 on the insurance of shipowners for maritime claims, available at: [https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32009L0020](https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32009L0020)"

literature:
  - "Norman A Martínez Gutiérrez, Limitation of Liability for maritime claims, in: The IMLI manual on international maritime law, Volume II: Shipping Law, Oxford University Press, 2016, available at: [https://www.iflos.org/wp-content/uploads/LLMC-Chapter-IMLI-Manual.pdf](https://www.iflos.org/wp-content/uploads/LLMC-Chapter-IMLI-Manual.pdf)"
  - "Guidelines In respect of Procedural Rules Relating to Limitation of Liability in Maritime Law, adopted at the 39th Conference of the CMI, held in Athens in October 2008, available at: [https://comitemaritime.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/468382-Rules-relating-to-Limitation-of-Liability-Guidelines-and-Commentary.pdfhttps://comitemaritime.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/468382-Rules-relating-to-Limitation-of-Liability-Guidelines-and-Commentary.pdf](https://comitemaritime.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/468382-Rules-relating-to-Limitation-of-Liability-Guidelines-and-Commentary.pdf)"
  - "Francesco Berlingieri, The Travaux Préparatoires of the LLMC Convention 1976 and of the Protocol of 1996, (CMI, 2000) 494"
  - "Patrick Griggs, Richard Williams and Jeremy Farr: Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims, 4th Edition (Lloyd’s Shipping Law Library, 2005)"
  - "James Severn, Edward White, The IMO’S unified interpretation of the LLMC and CLC conventions – when should a shipowner lose their right to limit liability? 26 January, 2023, available at: [https://www.penningtonslaw.com/news-publications/latest-news/2023/the-imo-s-unified-interpretation-of-the-llmc-and-clc-conventions-when-should-a-shipowner-lose-their-right-to-limit-liability](https://www.penningtonslaw.com/news-publications/latest-news/2023/the-imo-s-unified-interpretation-of-the-llmc-and-clc-conventions-when-should-a-shipowner-lose-their-right-to-limit-liability)"
  - "Albert G. Dugan, Jr., Esquire Cozen and O’Connor, Limitation of liability of carriers by sea and by land, 2000, available at: [https://www.cozen.com/admin/files/publications/dugan204880.pdf](https://www.cozen.com/admin/files/publications/dugan204880.pdf)"
  - "Information on JACKSON PARTON SOLICITORS webpage: [https://jacksonparton.com/limitation-conventions](https://jacksonparton.com/limitation-conventions)"

quiz:
  - question: "Which statement is correct in respect of concept of a limitation of liability in shipping?"
    options:
      - "it is the privilege accorded to a shipowner and certain other persons to limit their liability up to certain amount regardless of the actual amount of the claim;"
      - "it is the privilege accorded to a ships brokers and insurers to limit the amount of their liability, under certain circumstances, in respect of some contract claims;"
      - "it is the privilege accorded to any owner of any property to limit the amount of their liability, under certain circumstances, in respect of some contract claims."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Who are entitled to limit liability under the LMCC:"
    options:
      - "shipowner, charterer, manager and operator, salvors, insurers of liability of a seagoing ship;"
      - "shipowner, charterer, manager and operator, salvors, insurers of liability of a seagoing ship, as well, master and crew members;"
      - "only owner of a ship registered as such in a ship register."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Which claims can be considered as the maritime claims?"
    options:
      - "any claim concerning shipmaster debts whatsoever they arise;"
      - "any claim concerning or arising out of ship agent’s obligations;"
      - "any claim concerning or arising out of ownership, construction, possession, management, operation or trading of any ship."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "The following claims in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property, can be limited according to the LLMC:"
    options:
      - "only in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property occurring on board;"
      - "in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property occurring on board or in direct connexion with the operation of the ship or with salvage operations, and consequential loss resulting therefrom;"
      - "in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property occurring on board or in direct connexion with the operation of the ship."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "LLMC allows to limit claims in respect of loss resulting from delay in the carriage by sea of cargo, passengers or their luggage:"
    options:
      - "True;"
      - "False."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Which of the following claims are excluded from applicability of limitation according to the LLMC?"
    options:
      - "claims in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property (including damage to harbour works, basins and waterways and aids to navigation), occurring on board or in direct connexion with the operation of the ship or with salvage operations, and consequential loss resulting therefrom;"
      - "claims in respect of loss resulting from delay in the carriage by sea of cargo, passengers or their luggage;"
      - "nuclear damage claims;"
      - "claims in respect of other loss resulting from infringement of rights other than contractual rights, occurring in direct connexion with the operation of the ship or salvage operations;"
      - "claims in respect of the raising, removal, destruction or the rendering harmless of a ship which is sunk, wrecked, stranded or abandoned, including anything that is or has been on board such ship;"
      - "claims in respect of the removal, destruction or the rendering harmless of the cargo of the ship;"
      - "claims of a person other than the person liable in respect of measures taken in order to avert or minimize loss for which the person liable may limit his liability in accordance with this Convention, and further loss caused by such measures."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "Are some claims exempted from limitation of liability according to the LLMC?"
    options:
      - "Yes;"
      - "No."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Monetary unit used for calculation of limit of liability according to the LLMC is:"
    options:
      - "the gold standard as defined by the international monetary system;"
      - "the Special Drawing Right as defined by the International Monetary Fund;"
      - "established by national law of country where maritime claim was brought to the court."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "The limitation fund, constituted according to the LLMC, shall be distributed among the claimants in following:"
    options:
      - "in order of priority;"
      - "in proportion to their established claims against the fund;"
      - "the largest claims are paid first."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "Which of the following claims are excepted from limitation:"
    options:
      - "claims for salvage or contribution in general average;"
      - "claims in respect of loss resulting from delay in the carriage by sea of cargo, passengers or their luggage;"
      - "claims in respect of the removal, destruction or the rendering harmless of the cargo of the ship."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Under the LLMC a person liable shall not be entitled to limit his liability if:"
    options:
      - "it is proved that the loss resulted from the accident, committed without the intent to cause such loss and without knowledge that such loss would probably result;"
      - "it is proved that the loss resulted from his personal act, committed with the intention to cause such loss;"
      - "it is proved that the loss resulted from his personal act or omission, committed with the intent to cause such loss, or recklessly and with knowledge that such loss would probably result."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "In respect the counterclaims it is stated in the LLMC:"
    options:
      - "where a legal person entitled to limitation of liability has a claim against the claimant arising out of the same occurrence, the provisions of LLMC shall to both claims;"
      - "the LLMC does not provide any provisions on counterclaims;"
      - "where a person entitled to limitation of liability has a claim against the claimant arising out of the same occurrence, their respective claims shall be set off against each other and the provisions of LLMC shall only apply to the balance, if any."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "What separate limits of liability are prescribed by the LLMC?"
    options:
      - "general limits and the limit for passenger claims;"
      - "general limits, limit for salvors’ claims and the limit for passenger claims;"
      - "the limit for passenger claims and the limit for cargo claims;"
      - "claims in respect of damage to property and claims in respect of loss of life or personal injury."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Specific tonnage-based figures were set by the LLMC, providing the maximum financial liability in respect of all claims arising out of maritime incidents involving primarily personal, claims as well as property damage claims:"
    options:
      - "True;"
      - "False."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Limit of liability of shipowner according to the LLMC is:"
    options:
      - "based on the type of the ship involved in the incident;"
      - "based on the size of the ship involved in the incident;"
      - "based on the size of holds of the ship involved in the incident."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "In respect of claims arising on any district occasion for loss of life or personal injury to passengers of a ship, the limit of liability of the shipowner shall be:"
    options:
      - "limit of liability is based on ship tonnage;"
      - "an amount of 900,000 SDR;"
      - "an amount of 175,000 SDR multiplied by the number of passengers which the ship is authorised to carry according to the ship’s certificate."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "Maritime claim subject to limitation is:"
    options:
      - "claim of a person liable in respect of measures taken in order to prevent loss for which the person liable may limit his liability in accordance with LLMC, and further loss caused by such measures;"
      - "claim of a person other than the person liable in respect of measures taken in order to avert or minimize loss for which the person liable may limit his liability in accordance with LLMC, and further loss caused by such measures;"
      - "claim of any owner of any property in respect of measures taken in order to prevent loss for which the person liable may limit his liability in accordance with LLMC, and further loss caused by such measures."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "Claims for loss of life or personal injury to passengers of a ship under the LLMC shall mean any such claims brought by or on behalf of any person carried in that ship:"
    options:
      - "under a contract of passenger carriage;"
      - "who has no any contract;"
      - "under the contract of employment with the shipowner."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Directive 2009/20/EC requests to have insurance cover in respect of LLMC for:"
    options:
      - "only for EU flagged ships;"
      - "any ships of 300 gross tonnage or more entering into port of EU, except warships, auxiliary warships or other State owned or operated ships used for a non-commercial public service;"
      - "any ships entering into port of EU, except warships, auxiliary warships or other State owned or operated ships used for a non-commercial public service."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "Insurance under Directive 2009/20/EC comprises, for example:"
    options:
      - "indemnity insurance of the type currently provided by members of the International Group of P & I Clubs, and other effective forms of insurance (including proved self-insurance) and financial security offering similar conditions of cover;"
      - "indemnity insurance of the type currently provided only by members of the International Group of P & I Clubs;"
      - "indemnity insurance and other effective forms of insurance (including proved self-insurance) and financial security offering similar conditions of cover, except of the type currently provided by members of the International Group of P & I Clubs."
    correct_answer: 0
---

**Limitation of liability for maritime claims** is a legal concept, which allows the shipowner to limit his financial exposure for maritime claims up to a maximum sum regardless of the actual amount of the claims being brought against him.

The International Conference on the Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims, which adopted the **Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims 1976 (LLMC),** took place in London between 1 and 19 November 1976 under the auspices of the International Maritime Organization (IMO). LLMC entered into force on 1 December 1986.

Twenty years later at a Diplomatic Conference held at the IMO Headquarters in London (April/May 1996) the **text of a Protocol to the 1976 Limitation Convention** was agreed. **This Protocol of 1996 to amend the Convention on Limitation of Liability for Maritime Claims 1976** (LLMC 1996) entered into force internationally on 13 May 2004. This Protocol makes a radical difference to the amount to which owners (shipowners, charterer, operator or their insurer) of small tonnage can limit their liability.

According to LLMC **the persons entitled to limit their liability** are:

- ­shipowners of a seagoing ship,
- charterers of a seagoing ship (but not against shipowners),
- managers of a seagoing ship,
- operators of a seagoing ship,
- salvors,
- any person for whose act, neglect or default the shipowner or salvor is responsible,
- insurers of a seagoing ship.

Under the LLMC, the right to limit exists in respect of claims relating to seagoing ships.

LLMC **provides list of claims subject to limitation of liability**:

- claims in respect of loss of life or personal injury or loss of or damage to property (including damage to harbour works, basins and waterways and aids to navigation), occurring on board or in direct connexion with the operation of the ship or with salvage operations, and consequential loss resulting therefrom;
- claims in respect of loss resulting from delay in the carriage by sea of cargo, passengers or their luggage;
- claims in respect of other loss resulting from infringement of rights other than contractual rights, occurring in direct connexion with the operation of the ship or salvage operations;
- claims in respect of the raising, removal, destruction or the rendering harmless of a ship which is sunk, wrecked, stranded or abandoned, including anything that is or has been on board such ship;
- claims in respect of the removal, destruction or the rendering harmless of the cargo of the ship;
- claims of a person other than the person liable in respect of measures taken in order to avert or minimize loss for which the person liable may limit his liability in accordance with this Convention, and further loss caused by such measures.

It remains the case that claims and **counterclaims** arising out of the same occurrence must be set off against each other and limitation is to be applied only to the balance, if any, payable.

**LLMC lists the types of claims** in respect of which LLMC **shall not be applicable**:

- claims for salvage and general average;
- claims for oil pollution damages within the meaning of the International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, dated 29 November 1969 or of any amendment or Protocol thereto which is in force;
- nuclear damage claims;
- claims by servants of the shipowner or salvor whose duties are connected with the ship or the salvage operations;
- claims excluded by reservation.

A shipowner loses the right to limit the liability under the LLMC if it is proved that the loss resulted from his personal act or omission, committed with the intent to cause such loss, or recklessly and with knowledge, that such loss would probably result.

**LLMC** makes distinction between calculation of liability limit for passenger claims and for general claims (other than passengers' claims). The limits of liability were increased by the LLMC 1996.

The **limits of liability for general claims according to LLMC 1996 shall be calculated as follows**:

(a) respect of claims for loss of life or personal injury,

(i) 2 million Units of Account for a ship with a tonnage not exceeding 2,000 tons,

(ii) for a ship with a tonnage in excess thereof, the following amount in addition to that mentioned in (i):

- for each ton from 2,001 to 30,000 tons, 800 Units of Account;
- for each ton from 30,001 to 70,000 tons, 600 Units of Account; and
- for each ton in excess of 70,000 tons, 400 Units of Account,

(b) in respect of any other claims,

(i) 1 million Units of Account for a ship with a tonnage not exceeding 2,000 tons,

(ii) for a ship with a tonnage in excess thereof the following amount in addition to that mentioned in (i):

- for each ton from 2,001 to 30,000 tons, 400 Units of Account;
- for each ton from 30,001 to 70,000 tons, 300 Units of Account; and
- for each ton in excess of 70,000 tons, 200 Units of Account.

The limits of liability for passengers' claims according to LLMC 1996 shall be an amount of 175,000 Units of Account multiplied by the number of passengers, which the ship is authorized to carry according to the ship's certificate.

Units of Account are based on the daily conversion rates for Special Drawing Rights (SDRs) found on the International Monetary Fund IMF website: <https://www.imf.org/en/Search#q=special%20drawing%20rights&sort=relevancy>

IMO has adopted on 25 November 1999 Resolution A.898(21) Guidelines on shipowners' responsibilities in respect of maritime claims. Under the Guidelines the Shipowners should arrange for their ships appropriate insurance cover that complies with these Guidelines and should ensure that their ships have on board a certificate issued by the insurer. According to the Guidelines the shipowners should ensure that liability for relevant claims up to the limits set under the LLMC. If, however, the shipowner is entitled to invoke a limit of liability lower than that set by the LLMC, the insurance need only respond up to that lower limit. The insurance need respond only if:

- the shipowner's liability has been established at law; and
- the shipowner has complied with all the conditions of cover prescribed under the insurance contract.

Shipowners entering into ports of the European Union (EU) should have an insurance covering maritime claims subject to limitation under the LLMC as it is prescribed by Directive 2009/20/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 April 2009 on the insurance of shipowners for maritime claims (Directive 2009/20/EC). Certificates issued by its provider and carried on board the ship shall prove the existence of the appropriate insurance. This certificate is one of the documents to be inspected by the port State control in the EU member states. If the certificate is not carried on board, the expulsion order can be issued to the ship by the port State. As a result of the issuing of such an expulsion order, every Member State shall refuse entry of this ship into any of its ports until the shipowner is able to present appropriate certificate.
